Dorothy Kenyon Papers, 1850-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Dorothy Kenyon papers
1850 - 1998
Kenyon, Dorothy, 1888-1972
MS 85
69 boxes (29 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Lawyer, feminist, judge, and political activist. The Kenyon collection illuminates the continuity of social activism around such issues as race, class, poverty, and gender from the 1930s-60s. Topics reflected include worldwide suffrage; abortion rights; minority legal rights; the Equal Rights Amendment; and civil rights. Materials include writings, speeches, organizational records, photographs, memorabilia, and audio tapes of interviews and speeches. Significant correspondents include: Bella Abzug, Florence Allen, Roger Baldwin, Mary Dewson, India Edwards, Felix Frankfurter, Betty Friedan, Hubert Humphrey, Fiorello LaGuardia, Frieda Miller, Constance Baker Motley, Pauli Murray, Edmund Muskie, Eleanor Holmes Norton, Harriet Pilpel, Eleanor Roosevelt, Elihu Root, Anna Lord Strauss, and Harry Truman.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Kenyon, born in New York City on February 17, 1888, was the oldest of three children and the only daughter of prominent patent attorney William H. Kenyon, and Cincinnati, Ohio native Maria Wellington (Stanwood) Kenyon. Raised in the privileged environments of Manhattan's Upper West Side and her family's summer home in Lakeville, Connecticut, Kenyon excelled at the progressive Horace Mann High School from which she in graduated 1904. At Smith College she majored in economics and history and participated in numerous activities ranging from music to championship tennis and hockey. Kenyon was elected to Phi Beta Kappa in her junior year and graduated with an A.B. from Smith in 1908.
Though she often claimed that she had made the decision to become a lawyer when she was still a small child, Kenyon also conceded that she had "misspent" the years from 1908-1913 as a "social butterfly." It was only after a year in Mexico where she observed poverty and injustice at close range that Kenyon acquired her "slant to the left," decided upon her vocation, and transformed herself into a social activist. Kenyon entered New York University Law School at the age of 26 in 1914 and obtained her J.D. degree and admission to the New York Bar in 1917.
Unlike her two brothers Theodore Stanwood Kenyon and William Houston Kenyon Jr. who also became lawyers, Kenyon had a highly developed sense of public obligation kept her from joining the family law firm. Instead she began her legal career in 1917 with a brief stint as a law clerk in the New York firm Gwinn and Deming. Later that year she established herself more firmly in the legal profession through her work for the U.S. government in Washington, D.C., researching wartime labor patterns and collecting economic data for the 1919 Peace Conference. At the end of 1919 she returned to New York City and joined the firm Pitkin, Rosenson and Henderson. In 1925--the year she finally moved out of her father's house and into her own apartment--Kenyon also opened her own law office. In 1930 she joined forces with another woman lawyer, Dorothy Straus. They practiced law as Straus and Kenyon until 1939.
In keeping with her decision to work for social justice, Kenyon devoted a great deal of her energy in the 1930s and throughout her career to a variety of liberal and progressive causes, including the New Deal, women's rights, the labor movement, and consumer cooperatives. She served on the board of the American Civil Liberties Union from its inception in 1930. By the mid-1930s the combination of her legal credentials and her commitment to social justice won her various public appointments. In 1934, for example, she was appointed a member of the New York City Comptroller's Advisory Council on Taxes for the Relief of the Unemployed, and in 1936 she chaired a committee to study procedure in women's courts where she called for more sympathetic treatment of prostitutes and stronger prosecution of the men who patronized them. In 1936 she became the First Deputy Commissioner of Licenses in New York City and in 1937 she served as Vice Chair of the New York Commission of the National Public Housing Conference. Kenyon was a charismatic speaker and she regularly traveled around the U.S. lecturing about civil liberties, the law, women's equality, and numerous other subjects. She often reworked her addresses and published them as articles. Kenyon's writings appeared frequently in a variety of publications ranging from the Smith College Alumnae Quarterl, to American Girl Magazine to the Encyclopedia Britannica. At the end of 1939 Fiorello LaGuardia appointed Kenyon to fill a vacancy on the Municipal Court bench, a position in which she served until November of 1940. Despite her short tenure on the bench, Kenyon was known to many as "Judge Kenyon" for the rest of her life.
Dorothy Kenyon identified herself as a feminist and, though she played only a minor role in the suffrage movement, she served as an officer in several women's organizations that aimed to improve women's status in the 1920s and 1930s. Although she had lengthy and intense romantic relationships with various men (including Walcott Pitkin, Elihu Root Jr., and L.V. Pulsifer) over the course of her adult life, Kenyon was fiercely independent and made a conscious decision not to marry. Throughout her career she devoted special attention to the issues of jury service for women, equality in marriage, the legalization of birth control, and improved educational and economic opportunities for women. Kenyon gained national prominence as a feminist activist in 1938 when she was named the U.S. representative to the League of Nations Committee for the Study of the Status of Women, a group of seven lawyers charged with studying women's legal status internationally. World War II interrupted the committee's work and it was never completed. Kenyon resumed her commitment to improving women's status around the world through her work as the U.S. delegate to the United Nations Commission on the Status of Women from 1946-1950.
Already well-known in academic, legal, and political circles, in 1950 Dorothy Kenyon made national news when Senator Joseph R. McCarthy charged her with membership in numerous Communist-front organizations. Kenyon responded aggressively to McCarthy's accusations by declaring: "He's a lowdown worm and although it ought to be beneath my dignity to answer him, I'm mad enough to say that he's a liar and he can go to hell." As the first person to appear before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee that investigated McCarthy's charges she admitted that she had lent her name to various liberal and anti-fascist organizations, but forcefully denied that she had ever been a member or supporter of the Communist Party.
In the wake of her confrontation with McCarthy, Kenyon received widespread support from the liberal press and from respected public figures such as Eleanor Roosevelt. Her fearless defiance and unabashed condemnation of the Senator and his tactics undoubtedly contributed to his eventual downfall. Despite such vindication, the experience tarnished Kenyon's reputation to the degree that she never received another political appointment. Nevertheless, she sustained her busy law practice and, as progressive social movements resurged in the 1960s, escalated her already intense involvement in both national and local politics.
As a longtime supporter of civil rights, Kenyon prepared briefs for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund and the ACLU, fought segregation in the New York City schools, and participated in numerous civil rights marches. She participated in various aspects of President Johnson's War on Poverty and at age 80 she worked tirelessly and almost single-handedly to establish legal services for the poor on the Lower West Side. She continued her feminist activism throughout the 1950s and 1960s by pushing the ACLU to take a stand against sexist policies and institutions and, once they had done so, working with African-American activist and attorney Pauli Murray on preparing briefs for cases that challenged sex discrimination. In the last few years of her life Kenyon, along with many women of her generation who had opposed the ERA because of the negative implications they believed it held for working-class women, joined the pro-ERA forces. She also joined with much younger feminists in the emerging women's liberation movement where she participated in the 1971 Women's Strike for Equality and in the burgeoning movement to legalize abortion.
In addition to her numerous professional and political commitments, Dorothy Kenyon also maintained a busy social life. She had friends of all ages in New York and around the world, but her closest personal relationships centered around "Barn House," a rustic estate jointly owned by a small group of East coast liberal intellectuals in Chilmark on Martha's Vineyard. Kenyon joined Gertrude and Stanley King, Natalie and Adam Haskell, and Wolcott Pitkin in founding Barn House in 1919. Over the years Barn House members and guests included such notables as Crystal and Max Eastman, Roger and Evelyn Baldwin, Walter Lippman, Felix Frankfurter, and Sylvia Plath, among many others. In order to take advantage of its relaxing yet intellectually stimulating environment, Kenyon participated actively in administering Barn House and spent time there every summer from 1919 until 1971.
When Dorothy Kenyon was diagnosed with cancer in 1969 she concealed the severity of her illness from most people and refused to suspend or even curtail her legal or political work. Active and articulate as an advocate for social justice until the very end, Dorothy Kenyon died one week before her 84th birthday on February 11, 1972.
For for additional biographical information, see Bibliography.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dorothy Kenyon Papers consist of 29 linear feet of material dating from 1850-1998. The bulk of the papers date from 1888-1972 and focus on Kenyon's personal, professional, and political activities. Types of material include personal records and memorabilia; newspaper clippings; interview transcripts; financial records; family correspondence and memorabilia; personal and professional correspondence; published and unpublished writings; speeches; legal documents; organizational records; research files; photographs; miscellaneous notes, lists, and printed matter; and audiotapes of interviews and speeches.
Major subjects reflected in the collection include the status and role of women in the U.S. and internationally, U.S. and international law, domestic and foreign policy, abortion rights, civil rights, civil liberties, consumer rights, the cooperative movement, Democratic Party politics, Senator Joseph McCarthy, U.S. anti-communism, the War on Poverty in New York City, the Equal Rights Amendment, and the Women's Liberation movement. Organizations represented include the ACLU, NAACP, Americans for Democratic Action, various United Nations and League of Nations Committees, Mobilization for Youth, the Citizens Union of NYC, the American Labor Party, and others. The papers offer insight into the life of a pioneering woman lawyer, judge, and political figure. Kenyon was among the first women to gain admittance to the New York City Bar Association. She was active on local, state, national, and international levels in the fight for human rights, women's rights, and civil rights. In addition to illuminating Kenyon's own work for her causes, the papers document 20th century social reform movements in general. Race relations, urban reform policies, court reform, public housing, community development programs, and political activities from the 1890s to the 1970s are some of the many topics addressed in the papers.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into ten series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Family
III. Correspondence
IV. Speeches and Writings
V. Legal Practice
VI. Activities and Organization
VII. Research Files
VIII. Photographs
IX. Audiovisual Material
X. Oversize Material
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Dorothy Kenyon Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit Agents of Social Change: New Resources on 20th-century Women's Activism.
The Dorothy Kenyon Papers are also available on microfilm in the Sophia Smith Collection and in the circulating collection of Neilson Library. The latter is available on interlibrary loan. A reel index is also available. (Contact the SSC for more information).
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Dorothy Kenyon promised her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1951. Kenyon's brother and sister-in-law W. Houston Kenyon and Mildred Adams Kenyon donated the bulk of the papers in 1980. In 1998 Louise Wilby Knight (the granddaughter of Kenyon's first cousin Katherine Curtis Wilby) donated a small number of additional items including letters and audio-tapes. Additions to the collection are expected from time to time from other family members.
Search Terms
Abortion--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Anti-communist movements--United States--History--Sources; Citizen's Union (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Chilmark (Mass.)--History--Sources; Consumer cooperatives--United States--History--Sources; Consumers' League of New York City--History.; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; Feminists--United States---History--20th century--Sources; American Civil Liberties Union--History--Sources; League of Nations. Committee for the Study of the Legal Status of Women; Mobilization for Youth--History--Sources; NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund--History--Sources; New York (N.Y.)--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; United Nations Commission on the Status of Women--History--Sources; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Foreign Relations--History--Sources; Women (International law)--History--Sources; Women judges--United States--History--Sources; Women--Legal status, laws, etc.--History--20th century--Sources; Kenyon, Dorothy, 1888-1972; Abzug, Bella S., 1920- --Correspondence; Allen, Florence Ellinwood, 1884-1966--Correspondence; King, Stanley, 1883-1951; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorella Henry), 1882-1947; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957; Baldwin, Roger, 1884-1981--Correspondence; King, Gertrude Louisa Besse, 1881-1923; Pitkin, Walcott Homer, 1881- --Correspondence; Baldwin, Roger, 1884-1981; King, Gertrude Louisa Besse, 1881-1923; Pitkin, Walcott Homer, 1881-; Pulsifer, Lawson Valentine, 1881-1957; Root, Elihu, 1881-1967; Schneiderman, Rose, 1882-; Woodsmall, Ruth, 1883-1963
Additional Information
Bibliography
For additional biographical information see:
Susan M. Hartmann, The Other Feminists: Activists in the Liberal Establishment (Yale, 1998)
Linda Kerber, No Constitutional Right to be Ladies: Women and the Obligations of Citizenship (Hill and Wang, 1998)
Notable American Women, 1607-1950; a biographical dictionary (Harvard University Press, 1971)
Appendix: Dorothy Kenyon's Addresses and Articles by Subject
Listed chronologically under the following subjects: Anti-communism; Civil liberties; Civil rights and racism; Consumer and cooperative issues; Education; Labor issues; League of Nations; The Law and the legal profession; Political campaigns; Politics and political activism; Poverty; Tributes and introductions; United Nations and internationalism; Women's status and women's rights; World War II and American foreign policy; Miscellaneous.
Anti-communism (including McCarthyism)
Notes for address at meeting concerning Dies Committee 12/39 Box 19
Untitled notes for speech about Dies Committee and free speech issues 1940 Box 19
Untitled notes for remarks about subversiveness to Labor Club 1/40 Box 19
Untitled remarks regarding Dies Committee at Y.W.C.A. 4/40 Box 19
Untitled remarks for ACLU 6/40 Box 19
Untitled notes ["Congressional investigations when properly conducted"] 7/42 Box 20
"Are Our Civil Rights in Danger?" (remarks for radio broadcast) 3/48 Box 21
"The Image of the Thing We Hate," article for unidentified publication 4/50 Box 21
Untitled notes for "Meet the Press" broadcast ["need for Congressional immunity"]: manuscript 4/50 Box 21
"The Image of the Things We Hate Summer 1950 Box 21
"McCarran Act," speech delivered to Americans for Democratic Action-Bensonhurst 11/50 Box 21
"Man Becomes the Image of the Things He Hates," speech delivered at Cosmopolitan Club 1/51 Box 21
"A New Pilgrim's Progress 2/51 Box 21
"Threats to American Freedom," notes for speech delivered to Public Affairs Committee of YWCA 5/51 Box 21
"Threats to American Freedom," notes for speech before Far Rockaway Americans for Democratic Action 6/51 Box 21
"McCarran Act--Symbol of the Times," speech delivered to American Jewish Congress-Brooklyn 5/51 Box 21
"1st Freedom in 1951," notes for speech delivered to Connecticut Deans of Women 1951 Box 21
Untitled speech about anti-communism ["Age of fear, fear to express ideas"] delivered to YWCA Public Affairs Committee 11/51 Box 21
"Fear," speech delivered at New Era Club 12/51 Box 21
"Fear," speech delivered at the College of the City of New York Liberal Club 1/52 Box 21
"Let Freedom Speak," speech delivered to Council of Jewish Women of Jersey City 3/53 Box 21
"McCarthyism and Civil Liberties," notes for speech delivered at Americans for Democratic Action-North Westchester 4/53 Box 21
"McCarthyism," speech before Americans for Democratic Action-Gramercy Branch 6/53 Box 21
"Untitled remarks about NYC loyalty boards for television appearance 3/54 Box 22
"Abuses of Power of Some Congressional Investigating Committees," speech before National Jewish Veterans Association 4/54 Box 22
"People vs. McCarthy," remarks delivered at People vs. McCarthy meeting at Hunter College 5/54 Box 22
Untitled remarks about loyalty oaths in public housing ["very appealing idea but serious constitutional questions"] for television broadcast 6/54 Box 22
Untitled remarks for radio broadcast on anti-communism 11/54 Box 22
"McCarthy Censure," remarks for radio broadcast 11/54 Box 22
"McCarthy the Man," speech delivered to New Era Club 12/54 Box 22
"Convocation Notes," remarks delivered at Central Queens ADA 3/55 Box 22
"J. Robert Oppenheimer," speech introducing Oppenheimer at Women's City Club 4/55 Box 22
Untitled speech ["climate of opinion today"] delivered to American Jewish Congress 2/58 Box 22
"Gwinn Amendment circa 1950s Box 21
"From Another Ancient 2/67 Box 23
"The Nightmare Decade 10/71 Box 23
"I Protest: The Bishop and the House Un-American Activities Commission n.d. Box 23
Civil liberties
"Motion Picture Censorship" 8/31 Box 18
"Legal Aspects of Academic Freedom" 12/35 Box 18
"The Charter Nobody Knows," remarks for radio broadcast 10/38 Box 19
"Civil Rights and Mayor Hague," remarks for radio broadcast 1938 Box 19
Untitled notes for speech about Dies Committee and free speech issues 1940 Box 19
"Discussion--Free Speech," notes for remarks delivered to American Discussion League 1/40 Box 19
"More Discussion by the People," remarks delivered to Discussion League 1/40 Box 19
"Statement for Travelling Microphone" 4/40 Box 19
Untitled notes ["General--Freedom of religion first"] for remarks delivered at unidentified occasion 4/40 Box 19
"Freedom to Teach," speech for Council on Intolerance 5/40 Box 19
Untitled remarks for ACLU 6/40 Box 19
"Civil Liberties in War Time," radio speech for Humanity Guild 7/40 Box 19
"Three Point Program," article about free speech and Fifth Columnists 11/40 Box 19
"Free Speech," speech for NYU Civic Club 11/40 Box 19
"Significance of the Bill of Rights," speech at Governors Island 2/41 Box 20
"Can Democracy Survive?" speech for White Plains ACLU 3/41 Box 20
Untitled radio broadcast ["Somebody once called our bill of rights"] 3/41 Box 20
Untitled notes ["Democracy, dictatorship--civil liberties"] for speech to Workman's Circle 4/41 Box 20
"Is There a Civil Liberties Issue in the Detectaphone Case?" 11/41 Box 20
"Religion and Law," remarks for radio broadcast 6/43 Box 20
"An International Bill of Rights," speech at Free World Conference 10/43 Box 20
"Our Civil Liberties 12/45 Box 20
"Are Our Civil Rights in Danger?" remarks for radio broadcast 3/48 Box 21
Notes for speech on peacetime conscription delivered at the Rand School 10/48 Box 21
"Toward an International Bill of Rights," delivered to American Civil Liberties Union 1949 Box 21
"Civil Liberties, Democracy and Dictator Movements," speech delivered to the Saturday Evening Group late 1940s Box 19
"Are Civil Liberties in Danger?" speech delivered to Troy YWCA 1/50 Box 21
"Are We Undermining Our Civil Liberties," remarks for "Jubilee" radio broadcast 1/50 Box 21
Untitled speech ["Great battle of ideas going on"] about civil liberties delivered to Phi Beta Kappa 3/50 Box 21
"International Aspects of McCarran Act," speech delivered to East Side Branch of Americans for Democratic Action 10/50 Box 21
"Civil Liberties in the U.S.," speech celivered at Unity Church 2/51 Box 21
"Bill of Rights Week," speech delivered at Mabel Bacon Vocational High School 2/51 Box 21
"1st Freedom," speech about civil liberties given on unidentified occasion 1951 Box 21
"Civil Liberties--Current Issues," speech delivered to Americans for Democratic Action - Bayside 10/52 Box 21
"U.S. Constitution," remarks for radio broadcast 11/52 Box 21
"Civil Liberties," speech delivered to American Jewish Congress-Flatbush Branch 11/52 Box 21
"Civil Liberties," article for Civil Liberties Quarterly 3/53 Box 21
"Television at Legislative Hearings," speech delivered to Radio Institute of America Congress 4/53 Box 21
"Civil Liberties Today," speech delivered to Civil Liberties Union of Columbus, OH 4/53 Box 21
"The State of Civil Liberties," speech given at the Cooperative Institute--Bard College 7/53 Box 21
Untitled speech about civil liberties delivered to Americans for Democratic Action 9/53 Box 21
"Challenge to Civil Liberties," speech delivered to Cleveland Civil Liberties Union and Miami University of Ohio 11/53 Box 21
"Freedom is Never Won," speech delivered to Phi Beta Kappa chapter at Colby College 5/54 Box 22
Untitled speech about civil liberties delivered to United Neighborhood Houses 11/54 Box 22
"Academic Freedom," speech delivered to Central Nassau ADA 2/55 Box 22
"Civil Liberties," remarks for radio broadcast 3/55 Box 22
"Today's Challenge," speech delivered to Phi Beta Kappa at University of Rochester 4/55 Box 22
Untitled speech about wiretapping delivered at YWCA Convocation 4/55 Box 22
"Some Aspects of Civil Liberties," speech delivered to Westchester branch of American Jewish Congress 9/55 Box 22
"Man's Right to Knowledge and the Free Use Thereof," speech delivered to Phi Beta Kappa Association, Raleigh, NC 10/55 Box 22
"Some Aspects of Civil Liberties," speech delivered at unidentified occasion 1955 Box 22
"Survey of Civil Liberties," speech delivered to YWCA Public Affairs Committee 1/56 Box 22
"The Individual and the Law 5/56 Box 22
Untitled speech delivered to the Maryland branch of the ACLU 6/56 Box 22
"Wiretapping and Bugging," speech delivered at Williams College 4/58 Box 22
"Wiretapping, Eavesdropping and its Modern Equivalent, Bugging," speech delivered at unidentified occasion 1958 Box 22
"Civil Liberties Since Thomas Jefferson," speech delivered to West Virginia AAUW at West Liberty College 5/59 Box 22
"Civil Liberties in Education," speech delivered to Phi Beta Kappa initiates at Kalamazoo College 5/59 Box 22
"The 86th Congress, Civil Liberties, the Supreme Court, Congress and the Individual," speech delivered to ADA at Sarah Lawrence College 6/59 Box 22